A Guide to the Papers of William McFee, 1916-1951
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of William McFee, 1916-1951
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6241-b
This collection consists of 26 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 22 Jun 1965.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains manuscript for introduction to Innnocment Aloft.
Letters discuss the sale of his literary manuscripts; the publication of "Casuals of the Sea"; Joseph Conrad and Richard Curle's work on Conrad; royalties for "An Engineer's Notebook"; unauthorized reprints of his work; works on World War I; and his health and visits to England and Florida.
He also mentions "Command" as his favorite novel; Stefan Zeromski's "Ashes"; Joseph Henry Shorthouse's "John Inglesant"; Charles Reade's "The Cloister and the Hearth"; a Modern Language Association meeting in Chicago; Archibald Henderson; and George Bernard Shaw.
Correspondents include Lillian B. Bennett, Glen Walton Blodgett; Montgomery Evans, Crosby Gaige; Everett L. Getchell; E. J. Halter, Edward Lazare, Henry Goddard Leach, Christopher Morley, Howes Norris, Myriam Sieve, Harold Sinclair, and Paul M. Wheeler.
Contents List
- Introduction to Innocents Aloft, by Henry Justin Smith n.d., AMsS(bound). 15 p.
- Letters
  - William McFee to Howes Norris, Jr. 1922 Dec 17, ANS. 1 p.
    Provides autograph. Describes self as "a sea-going engineer."
  - W. McF. to Henry Goddard Leach 1923 Sep 15, ALS. 1 p.
    Is grateful for invitation to submit a topic; asks for suggestions and number of words. Is anxious to finish novel before taking on fresh work.
  - W. McF. to "Dear John" 1924 Jul 30, ALS. 1 p.
    Has located ms. of [Letters From] an Ocean Tramp, about which John had inquired.
  - W. McF. to [Crosby] Gaige 1924 Aug 7, ALS. 1 p.
    Replies to prospective buyer of ms. of The Ocean Tramp. Has asked his mother to send all other of his mss. from London. Invites Gaige to visit him in Westport, Conn.
  - W.McF. to Editor of The World1925 Apr 22, TLS. 1 p.
    W/clipping of the letter as printed in the paper.] Printed 1925 April 25 in The World.Complains that wireless operators on ships and aircraft are called "heroic" while others more worthy are not.
  - W. McF. to [Lillian B.] Bennett 1928 Jan 24, ALS. W/env. 2 p.
    Intends to get "Max" to autograph book; plans return to England for summer.
  - W. McF. to L. B. [1928 Feb 22]Wednesday, ALS. W/env. 3 p.
    Complains about attacks of lumbago and rheumatism. May go on a cruise to England. Would like to sell his [Westport, Conn.] house.
  - W. McF. to "Dear Mr. Milkman" 1928 Mar 22, ANS. 1 p.
    Has just returned from hospital. Sends compliments.
  - W. McF. to Miss Myriam Sieve 1928 Jul 26, TLS. 1 p.
    Replies to letter received while in England. Discusses merits of several books on the late war and remarks on the need to resist aggressors. Would like to read Ashes by Stefan Zeromski.
  - W. McF. to M. S. 1928 Sep 10, ALS. 2 p.
    Discusses historical novels. Mentions The Cloister and the Hearth by Charles Reade. Recommends John Inglesant by J[oseph]; H[enry] Shorthouse. Gives travel plans.
  - W. McF. to L. B. 1931 Jan 14, ALS. W/env. 2 p.
    Refuses to spend $25 for a first edition for a friend who wants only "an ordinary copy." Dislikes New York.
  - W. McF. to Everett L. Getchell 1931 Feb 4, TLS. 1 p.
    Comments to professor at Boston University on subject of posterity. Enjoys the notice of his contemporaries.
  - W. McF. to Dr. [Paul M.] Wheeler 1931 Jun 3, TLS. 2 p.
    Complains that his material has been reprinted so often without his receiving payment. Illustrates point with examples. Refers to the "mimeograph mind" of the book compiler.
  - W. McF. to Edward Lazare of G. A. Baker and Co., Inc. 1935 Aug 16, TLS. 1 p.
    Describes events of past year as a reason for not writing earlier. Had gone to Florida for winter, thence to London because of family illness, death.
  - W. McF. to E. L. 1935 Oct 28, TLS. 1 p.
    Intends to revise copy of his early book containing poem "About the Apprentices." Desires to change some of the prose; regrets previous issuance of this book.
  - W. McF. to E. L. 1936 Jan 16, TLS. 1 p.
    Invites Lazare to visit at new house; asks about possible job opening for son of an old friend.
  - W. McF. to "Dear Sir" 1940 May 23, ALS. 1 p.
    [Relates publishing history of Casuals of the Sea.]
  - W. McF. to E. J. Halter 1945 May 9, TLS. 1 p.
    Says that while Casuals of the Sea has been his best selling novel, his own preference has always been Command.
  - W. McF. to Montgomery Evans 1951 Oct. 2, TLS. W/env. 1 p.
    Refers to [Richard Henry Parnell] Curle's work on [Joseph] Conrad, and to Conrad's visit to New York. Mentions Archibald Henderson, [George Bernard] Shaw; his deafness.
  - W. McF. to M. S. n. y. Oct. 12, ANS. 1 p.
    Greetings. Thanks for letter.
  - W. McF. to L. B. n. d. Tuesday, ALS. W/env. 2 p.
    Sends two books: the Lewis book is to go to president of United Fruit Co., the other to George Keating. Refers to latter's $25 Conrad memorial.
  - John Held Jr. to Crosby Gaige n. d., ANS. 1 p.
    McFee can be reached in Westport.
  - W. McF. to [Christopher] Morley n. d. Thursday A. M., ALS. 1 p.
    Asks C. M. how to get to Chicago for meeting of the Modern Language Assn; would like a reduced fare. Complains of publishers' bad treatment of authors and rails against "free lunch counters in literature."
- Miscellaneous
  - "William McFee" by Harold Sinclair, with "Checklist clipping Bibliography" on McFee. May 1937, Magazine. 2 p.
  - "I Have Appendicites [sic]": self-portrait by W. McF. n. d., Pen and ink. Sketch. 1 p.
    Annotated and signed in author's hand.